<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>presenting on Jess Pomfret</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/tags/presenting/</link><description>Recent content in presenting on Jess Pomfret</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jpomfret.github.io/tags/presenting/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>T-SQL Tuesday #133: What (Else) Have You Learned from Presenting?</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#133-what-else-have-you-learned-from-presenting/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#133-what-else-have-you-learned-from-presenting/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://lisagb.info/archives/77" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/tsqltues.png"
loading="lazy"
alt="T-SQL Tuesday Logo"
>&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It’s December, the last T-SQL Tuesday for 2020. I’ve managed to participate in seven this year, including hosting in February – I wonder if in 2021 I will be able to complete a full year. I always look forward to these monthly blog parties, so thanks to Lisa for hosting this month. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lisa has asked us to share something we’ve learnt from presenting that didn’t relate directly to the topic we were presenting on.  I think this is a great topic. We already know that to present on a topic you have to really know it, so preparing for a presentation does wonders for your own personal knowledge on that topic.  Lisa has identified another bonus- all the ancillary knowledge that comes along with it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I gave my first presentation in June 2018, and although it’s only been around 2.5 years since then, I have learnt so much from both presenting and contributing to the community.  I have a couple of areas I’m going to mention here.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="git--github">&lt;strong>Git &amp;amp; GitHub&lt;/strong>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My first real contributions were not presenting but writing code and tests for dbatools.  Writing PowerShell was not something that was new to me, so I felt comfortable writing the function I wanted to add. Through code review it did get some much needed tweaking to ensure it met the standards and format of the project.  Getting the code from my laptop into the dbatools GitHub repo was another story – it was totally foreign to me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Luckily the dbatools team is fantastic. They have written great guides on using git and GitHub in order to make your first pull request, and Chrissy even coached me through how to get my code into GitHub that first time. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>As I continued to contribute I got more familiar with using Git and GitHub for source control, and since then there have been many times where I’ve needed that knowledge both for community projects as well as my real job. I even host my &lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/jpomfret/demos" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>presentation demos and slides&lt;/a> there now.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="docker">&lt;strong>Docker&lt;/strong>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I think one thing that every presenter has had to learn is how to set up some form of a lab to be able to run demos in a reliable and repeatable way.  I started off with a VM on my local laptop that I could connect to and run demos against. This took some learning to get the networking setup. Something I still consider a weak area!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After a while I started reading more about containers, and specifically running SQL Server in containers.  I now (where possible) run all my demos for presentations against demo environments in containers that run on my laptop. I have already written a post on this, &lt;a class="link" href="https://jesspomfret.com/data-compression-containers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Data Compression Demos in Containers&lt;/a>, but this has given me a great opportunity to learn and play with a really interesting technology.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of the main benefits I see when running demos against containers is how easy it is to wipe away your practice runs and have a fresh environment ready for the presentation.  I’ve even built pester tests into my setup script to ensure everything is in the perfect state for the demo gods. I’ve also written about that if you’re interested in what I test, &lt;a class="link" href="https://jesspomfret.com/demo-gods-pester/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Keeping the demo gods at bay with Pester&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="summary">&lt;strong>Summary&lt;/strong>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It took me a long time to make the first step into giving back and presenting content in front of people, but if I look back at the fun I’ve had over the last 2.5 years and all the knowledge I’ve gained it’s easy to see what a great decision that was. If you are considering speaking I would highly recommend giving it a go – as Lisa mentioned in her prompt, Allen White’s famous speech, everyone has something to teach.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks again for hosting Lisa, and I look forward to reading all the other responses.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>T-SQL Tuesday #119 - Changing your mind</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#119-changing-your-mind/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#119-changing-your-mind/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="http://workingwithdevs.com/tsql2sday-119-changing-your-mind/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/tsqltues.png"
loading="lazy"
>&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It’s time for our monthly T-SQL Tuesday blog party again and we have another interesting prompt to write about. Thanks goes to Alex Yates (&lt;a class="link" href="http://workingwithdevs.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>b&lt;/a>|&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/_AlexYates_" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>t&lt;/a>) for hosting this month.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I’ve thought about this a lot over the last few days and really wanted to find a technical topic to write about, but over and over I came back to the same thoughts. This last week I attended two conferences and gave three presentations (one topic twice), and I still can’t believe I’ve given a single technical presentation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Allen White (&lt;a class="link" href="http://dataperfpro.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>b&lt;/a>|&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/SQLRunr" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>t&lt;/a>) has a famous spiel that he gives before every one of his presentations, encouraging his audience that everyone has something they can teach others. I created my PASS profile in 2011, and that was about the time I first heard Allen present. I remember laughing to myself that I would never be able to do that.  Giving presentations during my college years was something I dreaded, why on earth would I volunteer now to do that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Well, fast forward to June 2018, I gave &lt;a class="link" href="https://jesspomfret.com/first-user-group-presentation-i-survived/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>my first user group presentation&lt;/a>. I stepped way out of my comfort zone for that, but since then I have presented 11 additional times.  I’ve presented at a mixture of SQL Saturdays, online virtual groups and conferences, and every time I’ve got extremely nervous beforehand, and experienced an unbelievable high after.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This past week I gave my DSC &amp;amp; SQL Server presentation on Friday in Columbus at &lt;a class="link" href="https://dogfoodcon.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>DogFoodCon&lt;/a> (a great conference with a very different crowd than my usual data platform events) and then I gave two sessions at &lt;a class="link" href="https://sqlsaturday.com/907/eventhome.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>SQL Saturday Pittsburgh&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At this point I still feel like I’m not really a speaker, every time I walk into the speaker room at an event I expect someone to ask what I’m doing in there. However, I’ve received a lot of great feedback, and more importantly had a lot of great conversations with people about things they learnt in my session. I’m getting there.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The other amazing part of this adventure is I’ve had so much fun, I’ve met and become friends with some great people and I’ve traveled as far as Germany to explore the world and deliver my sessions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I can 100% say I’ve changed my opinion on whether I can become a speaker in this community, and I’ve bought into Allen’s spiel that everyone has something to give back. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you are reading this and laughing to yourself that it can’t mean you, it does! Maybe you’re not ready to speak, but start a blog and share some things you’ve done – other people are one month behind you, trying to work out how to do what you just did. If writing isn’t your style, go contribute some code to open source software- &lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/sqlcollaborative/dbatools" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>dbatools&lt;/a> and &lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/sqlcollaborative/dbachecks" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>dbachecks&lt;/a> are on GitHub and always looking for new contributors. Go squash some bugs or add new functionality.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks again to Alex for the great prompt.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>T-SQL Tuesday #112 - Dipping into your Cookie Jar</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#112-dipping-into-your-cookie-jar/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#112-dipping-into-your-cookie-jar/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://nocolumnname.blog/2019/03/05/t-sql-tuesday-112-dipping-into-your-cookie-jar/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/tsqltues-300x300.png"
loading="lazy"
>&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It’s T-SQL Tuesday time again and our host this week, Shane O&amp;rsquo;Neill (&lt;a class="link" href="https://nocolumnname.blog/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>b&lt;/a>|&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/SOZDBA" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>t&lt;/a>), has challenged us to a humble brag. This really is a challenge for most of us as we do awesome things quietly, so thanks to Shane for forcing us to share some ‘cookies’.  This is also the second time in a couple of weeks that &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.amazon.com/Cant-Hurt-Me-Master-Your-ebook/dp/B07H453KGH" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>David Goggins’ book&lt;/a> has been mentioned, which means I need to move it up on my to-read list.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Imposter syndrome is something a lot of us struggle with. I am going to share a couple of things that I’m proud of and that I can look back on when things get tough.  As I’ve written before I’m working hard on stepping out of my comfort zone to prepare and deliver technical presentations. Recently I’ve been building a presentation that has caused me to wonder many times, what was I thinking.  Hopefully this recap will remind me that I can do it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="automating-nonproduction-refreshes">Automating Nonproduction Refreshes&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This first story is a technical one. I was working on a project a year or so ago that involved complicated changes to business processes and therefore it was decided that development and test environments needed to be as similar to production as possible.  This meant that I was inundated with requests to take backups of production and restore to many nonproduction environments.  This got old fast.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The process not only involved the backup/restore piece, the data in production was both sensitive and encrypted using TDE.  I started writing PowerShell scripts for each step in the process, restoring certificates and databases, unencrypting and then removing certificates and then masking the sensitive data (which involved calling a T-SQL stored procedure built by my colleague, &lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/awickham" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Andrew&lt;/a>).  This was fine to begin with, but as the production data grew the process took longer and longer, which meant that the nonproduction environment was unavailable for longer each time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After awhile this process was no longer acceptable because the test environments were down for too long. I met with the team and we came up with a plan.  We ended up agreeing that we would create a process to create ‘restore points’.  These would basically be points in time from production, that were prepared for nonproduction use, off hours in a temporary environment.  I utilized a combination of &lt;a class="link" href="https://developer.ibm.com/urbancode/products/urbancode-deploy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Urban Code Deploy&lt;/a> (UCD), a product we already had in house, and PowerShell scripts to give the developers the power to first create a restore point, and then to be able to refresh environments from these prepackaged backups.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The process in UCD to create a restore point took the scripts I had been using manually and packaged them up so the result was a folder of already unencrypted, masked databases that were safe to restore to any of the test environments.  Everyone was happy, I no longer had to do this mundane, boring request and the team could refresh whenever they needed to, only having to wait for the restore to finish.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is still plenty of room for improvement in this process. Perhaps we could use some kind of database cloning technology to minimize space requirements and reduce the time to restore. Another option would be running the databases in containers. The developers could then just spin up an environment when they needed to test something. For now, though, the process is making everyone’s life easier, and that was a big win for both myself and the project team.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="speaking-in-front-of-people">Speaking in Front of People!&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The second humble brag is that I’m speaking in front of people! A year ago I had just agreed to give my first user group presentation and I was terrified.  I had set a goal of giving back to the community by blogging/writing and speaking, but the speaking part was by far the most difficult for me to get my head around. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thinking back to college, I dreaded finding out that class projects included final presentations. This hasn’t changed, and now I was voluntarily going to present.  In the last year I’ve put together a pretty decent hour-long presentation on data compression that I’ve delivered not once, but four times.  Each time I’ve grown in confidence and felt more like I could be myself in front of a crowd.  One of my demos that I’m particularly proud of shows how data compression affects the data storage on the page.  I then &lt;a class="link" href="https://jesspomfret.com/data-compression-internals/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>wrote about this demo&lt;/a> and it was picked up and featured in &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.brentozar.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Brent Ozar’s&lt;/a> weekly links.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I’ve also had my second presentation topic selected for &lt;a class="link" href="https://datagrillen.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>DataGrillen&lt;/a> and &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.sqlsaturday.com/827/eventhome.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>SQL Saturday Cincinnati&lt;/a>. I’m working hard to make sure I can deliver an informative and useful session on the possibilities of using PowerShell Desired State Configuration to install and configure SQL Server. During this process it has often felt like I’ve bitten off more than I can chew, both on my topic choice and the fact I submitted it to an international conference with a superstar line up of speakers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But here’s to remember the wins, and knowing I’ve already overcome these same doubts and challenges to get my first presentation up and running. This will be a great post to come back to when I need to dip in the cookie jar.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>T-SQL Tuesday #111 - What is Your "Why"?</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#111-what-is-your-why/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#111-what-is-your-why/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://andyleonard.blog/2019/02/t-sql-tuesday-111-what-is-your-why/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/tsqltues-300x300.png"
loading="lazy"
>&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It’s T-SQL Tuesday again and thanks goes this week to our host Andy Leonard (&lt;a class="link" href="https://andyleonard.blog" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>b&lt;/a>|&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/AndyLeonard" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>t&lt;/a>). Andy has picked a great topic on why we do the things we do. With our hectic lives it’s good sometimes to sit down and have a think about something like this.  I’ve split my ‘what I do’ up into three buckets that, although are separate, have a lot of common ‘whys’.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="database-administrator">Database Administrator&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I have been a SQL Server DBA since 2011, and it was kind of an accident.  I graduated from The University of Akron with an undergraduate degree in Information Systems and a Masters in Business Administration, and marched off into the real world to find the perfect job.  I had many interviews for all kinds of IT related positions and although I thought most of them went well and would provide a good first job for me, the folks on the other side of the table didn’t seem to agree. Part of this was I required a visa to work in the US. It was always going to be challenging to convince someone to take a chance on a new graduate and then spend a lot of money and effort to file paperwork.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was about a week or two away from having to leave the country as my current visa was expiring, when I got a job offer as a SQL Server DBA.  I had gone on this interview without much hope. I didn’t feel like I was qualified, and although I enjoyed my databases classes in college I had very little experience actually doing this kind of work (I’d worked as a grad assistant CMS web admin for the past two years).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first few weeks of this position were rough. I still remember one of the first days, I was being trained to handle simple change requests (adding permissions, changing agent jobs, creating tables etc.), my colleague told me to right click on a particular job and select properties so we could change the schedule.  I had zero idea how to even find the job in management studio. I just looked at him blankly as he had to walk me through expanding ‘SQL Server Agent’ and then ‘Jobs’.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One thing I’m pretty proud of is I work hard at learning and growing. I like to know how things work and why, and although I was well out of my depth to start with I managed to gain a lot of knowledge in this role.  I got more comfortable handling change requests and eventually got to the point where I could get through a two week on call rotation without having to wake up the senior DBA, even when our reasonably complicated replication setup caught fire in the middle of the night for no reason.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After four years I moved companies to my current role, still working as a SQL Server DBA.  It’s been over 8 years since that first day, and I still love what I do.  I think the main reason is that the learning never stops.  There is always new challenges to attack, new ideas to test out, and with that comes so many opportunities.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="crossfitter">Crossfitter&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.crossfit.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>CrossFit&lt;/a>, for those of you that don’t know, is a workout regime consisting of “constantly varied high-intensity functional movements”. It combines cardio, weightlifting and gymnastics into a workout that will leave you led on the floor wondering why it was so hard. In my opinion though the beauty of CrossFit is what happens around the workout. You end up with a random group of people all struggling through the workout of the day (WOD) together, cheering each other on and then reminiscing about how they made it through.  It’s not at all unlike team sports, and that’s why when I found CrossFit it filled a huge void.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I played soccer (proper football) for the first 23 years of my life. I’m pretty sure as soon as I could walk I had a football at my feet.  When my senior season of college was over in 2009 I stopped playing and I stopped working out. I didn’t stop eating like an athlete though – bring on the weight gain!  Once I started CrossFit I found the same things I’d loved about football - a group of people all working towards the same goals coupled with the challenge of trying to constantly improve at something.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>CrossFit never seems to get any easier and I think that’s why I love it. I recently had a memory pop up on Facebook that 7 years ago I had got my first handstand pushup.  These days I can (not going to say easily) get 50 in a workout, but now I’m working towards being able to walk on my hands.  The challenges never end.  Whenever I reach a goal, there is always the next one. Can I lift more weight, can I do that workout faster, can I catch my wife (no is the answer here…). These challenges, and the amazing community at my gym, are why I’ll keep on Crossfitting.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="community-collaborator">Community Collaborator&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>At some point in 2018 I decided it was time. Time to stop being a lurker and to give something back to the amazing SQL Server and PowerShell communities. I started this blog, actually with a &lt;a class="link" href="https://jesspomfret.com/t-sql-tuesday-99/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>T-SQL Tuesday post&lt;/a>, and I signed up to present at my local user group in Cleveland.  I’ve mentioned this before, but this was way out of my comfort zone. The thought of standing in front of people and sharing what I think I know is terrifying. However, it has also turned out to be an amazing experience so far.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When I started out as a DBA, remember - knowing almost nothing, I leaned heavily on the community. I signed up for newsletters and RSS feeds, trying to read as much as I could.  I also attended our user group meetings and some nearby SQL Saturdays and although I was terrible at the networking portion of the events, I got a lot of great tips from the sessions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This past weekend I presented at SQL Saturday Cleveland. This was my second SQL Saturday as a speaker and I still can’t believe how much I loved it.  The whole day I was on a high. I gave my session at 8:30am and it went pretty well. I attended a few great sessions, had lunch with some amazing friends and even recorded a &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9Zk3R7_Pr-U" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>video with Bert&lt;/a> for his famous YouTube channel.  I got to work on Monday and had a notification from LinkedIn that I had a message. Someone had taken the time to write and let me know they’d enjoyed my session and that it had been useful.  This made my day, and made me realize I’m actually giving something back.  I still have a long way to go but I’m definitely making steps in the right direction.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="summary">Summary&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Throughout the three parts of my life I’ve talked about there have been a few common themes.  I love a good challenge - from standing in front of a room of peers and giving a presentation to trying to walk on my hands, these targets that are just out of reach provide a lot of motivation to me.  What goes hand in hand with this is my desire to keep learning and growing. The DBA landscape is never going to stay still or constant, and with that there are forever going to be opportunities for me to evolve as a data professional.  That’s pretty exciting, and that’s why I do what I do.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>First User Group Presentation - I Survived!</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/first-user-group-presentation-i-survived/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jpomfret.github.io/first-user-group-presentation-i-survived/</guid><description>&lt;p>Well tonight marks three weeks since I gave my first user group presentation and you know what, it’s been a total whirlwind since then so I’ve had little time to reflect.  Myself and the fiancé closed on our first house and my parents flew in to visit. It’s very useful to have people on hand the first couple of weeks so we didn’t feel like completely unqualified homeowners. I spent some time right after the presentation to start breathing again and to jot down some thoughts, but this is the first chance I’ve had to report back.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>TL;DR I didn’t die, the SQL Server community is fantastic and I have amazing supportive friends.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/Pittfurg/status/1004125722082934784" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://twitter.com/Pittfurg/status/1004125722082934784&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-present">Why Present?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The answer to this is twofold. Firstly this year I’ve challenged myself to get more involved in the SQL Server community. For several years now I’ve attended user group meetings, SQL Saturday’s and even made it to the PASS Summit a couple of times, but I’ve never contributed anything. It’s been all take.   Last year I got involved with dbatools and that started my quest to return the favour.  I’m still currently wrestling with the ideas of “who wants to listen to what I have to say” and “do I really have anything to contribute anyway,” but I’m doing my best to keep one foot in front of the other and see what happens.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Secondly, whenever I review my strengths and weaknesses at annual review time, communication, or more precisely public speaking is always something that I consider a weakness.  I’m not sure of a better way to improve in this area than to put myself out there and practice, so here’s to some professional development. I’m certain that gaining some knowledge, experience and confidence in this area will help me in many areas of my life.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-to-present">What to Present?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I ended up presenting on SQL Server data compression.  I talked about the types of data compression, and how the internals work before focusing on what you can compress, how to compress and how to decide what should be compressed.  This topic stemmed mainly from an issue at work where data compression was implemented with a large performance benefit.  This issue at work also encouraged me to spend some time looking at dbatools and compression. There were existing commands for Set-DbaDbCompression and Test-DbaDbCompression that I added some improvements to, and then I added Get-DbaDbCompression.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The culmination of both the issue at work and working on dbatools commands for compression left me feeling like this was a great topic to share.  Since 2016 SP1 data compression is now a standard level feature, opening up the possibilities to a lot more people.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="improvements">Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Overall I think the presentation went well, I delivered most of what I had planned on saying and my demo’s did a decent job of explaining the process for deciding what to compress and then applying compression through T-SQL, SSMS and PowerShell.  I was lucky to have some great friends in the audience (&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/awickham" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Andrew&lt;/a>, &lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/Pittfurg" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Drew&lt;/a> and &lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/erinstellato" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Erin&lt;/a>) who asked great questions which helped me to drive home certain points.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My timing was definitely a bit off. I’d prepared for what I thought would be 45-60 minutes of content and it was a bit shorter than that.  I plan on adding some additional content and delivering slightly slower the next time I give this talk to fix this problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I got some great feedback both from the speaker evaluations and from &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.sqlskills.com/blogs/erin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Erin Stellato&lt;/a> who went above and beyond my request for any tips and feedback she may have.  I’ll make sure to incorporate some real life stories on where compression has had an impact as well as adding some more demos.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="whats-next">What’s next?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>That’s right, there is a next! I took a chance and submitted my session to &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.sqlsaturday.com/736/eventhome.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>SQL Saturday Columbus&lt;/a> and was lucky enough to be selected.  I’ve been to quite a few SQL Saturdays in Cleveland, Columbus, Pittsburgh and even Minneapolis, but this will be my first as a speaker.  If you’re in the area on July 28th and want to learn more about data compression I’ll be on at 8:30am in Room 6.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I’m also going to work on some blog posts around data compression and the dbatools commands so watch out for that also.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>