<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>personal on Jess Pomfret</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/categories/personal/</link><description>Recent content in personal on Jess Pomfret</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jpomfret.github.io/categories/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>T-SQL Tuesday #134 - Give me a break</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#134-give-me-a-break/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#134-give-me-a-break/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://jimbabwe.co.za/2021/01/04/tsqltuesday-134-invitation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/tsqltues.png"
loading="lazy"
alt="T-SQL Tuesday Logo"
>&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It’s the first T-SQL Tuesday of 2021, and James Mcgillivray (&lt;a class="link" href="https://jimbabwe.co.za/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>b&lt;/a>|&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/JamesMcG_MSBI" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>t&lt;/a>) is our host for January’s edition of this monthly blog party.  This month’s topic is around how we escape with vacation/holiday plans.  They gave us a few options on what to blog about and I’m going to take you on a virtual trip to Hawaii.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-the-best-vacationholiday-youve-ever-had">What is the best vacation/holiday you’ve ever had?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The best holiday I’ve ever had would have to be my honeymoon to Hawaii in 2018.  We spent 10 days exploring two islands and it was fantastic.  This is a great prompt as it has encouraged me to look back at my photos from that time and record some memories.  I have a pretty horrible memory, but that trip I will never forget. I hope that as you follow along with this post it will take you on a virtual holiday, welcome to ‘Team Jelcie’s Hawaii Honeymoon’.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="first-stop-maui">First stop Maui&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/FB_IMG_1540745531257.jpg"
loading="lazy"
alt="Jess &amp; Kelcie in Wedding outfits"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We got married on Saturday 27th of October 2018 in Ohio, not far from where we were living.  We were lucky to be surrounded by friends and family from both sides of the Atlantic, and apart from the constant rain all day, we had an amazing time. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>The following Monday we boarded a plane for Maui, Hawaii. It’s actually a longer flight time from Ohio to Maui than it is from Ohio to England.  Until we started planning this trip I had no idea how far off the coast of the continental USA it actually is.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of the benefits of this long flight time, jet lag had us waking up really early the first few days. We brewed some coffee in the room and took it down to the beach.  We were treated to the most amazing sunrises. The longer we stood there the more impressive the colours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/20181031_062105-scaled.jpg"
loading="lazy"
alt="Hawaii sunrise from the beach on Maui"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We’d planned our honeymoon using a travel agent,  so we pre-booked several excursions for our time away. The first being a sunset sail, which didn’t disappoint, since the sunsets were almost as beautiful as the sunrises.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/20181031_174225-1024x768.jpg"
loading="lazy"
alt="Picture of the sunset from our sailing boat"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The second excursion was one of the top memories of the trip, a snorkelling excursion to &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Molokini" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Molokini&lt;/a>, a ‘crescent-shaped, partially submerged volcanic crater’. I have never seen such clear water- you could see the bottom of the ocean and it was 40m deep in parts.  Also so many fish, every shape and size and colour. It was fantastic. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>We also hiked, dropped into a Crossfit gym, relaxed and ate plenty of delicious food, before it was time to board a flight to the next stop of our trip.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="second-island--kauai">Second island – Kauai&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>A short flight and we were on our second island.  At the airport I surprised Kelc by renting a Jeep for us to drive, her dream car, and it made our options of exploring Kauai a lot easier. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first picture I have, apart from the Jeep, was this Poke bowl.  We found this stand inside a grocery store, and it was probably the most delicious thing I’ve ever eaten – this was not the only time we ate this within our few days here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/20181103_132824-768x1024.jpg"
loading="lazy"
alt="Poke bowl"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This island felt totally different from Maui. Maui wasn’t that commercialised, but Kauai was even less so. We definitely felt like we were enjoying island life in all its glory.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We love to hike and we were not disappointed. One of the days we took the Jeep up to Waimea Canyon and hiked several miles into these hidden waterfalls.  There was a lot of elevation gain and at some points there were helicopters flying in the canyon beneath us.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/20181104_112329-768x1024.jpg"
loading="lazy"
alt="Waimea Canyon waterfall"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We were also lucky to see some Hawaiian Monk Seals. I love seals, so it was amazing to see them rock up on to the beach to rest in the sun for the day.  They are protected so when they do beach themselves volunteers run out and cordon them off so they are protected for the day.  When the sun sets they roll and wiggle down the beach and back into the ocean, prompting the volunteers to collect their signs and wait to see where they appear the next day. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/20181104_072245-768x1024.jpg"
loading="lazy"
alt="Monk seals resting in the sun"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our third excursion was an ATV trip through a historic sugar plantation. This was great- we got filthy and had a lot of fun touring around beautiful scenery that’s featured in many movies, including Jurassic Park, although we saw no dinosaurs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/IMG-20181105-WA0081-769x1024.jpg"
loading="lazy"
alt="Muddy, driving an ATV"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="summary">Summary&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Overall we both thoroughly enjoyed this holiday, a great mix of relaxation and adventure.  I think we would both say that Maui was our favourite of the two islands, but Kauai offered a great second perspective of what Hawaii is all about.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I really enjoyed looking back over my Hawaii trip, and I hope you enjoyed this virtual holiday in one of the most beautiful spots in the world.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="whats-next">What’s next?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>If I was to write about my next dream holiday, it would be the Maldives. Back in June, when we had almost nothing to look forward to, we booked a 10 day holiday in the Maldives for January 16th, 2021. It felt like ages away, and surely things would be better by then. Well, if you’re reading this when it was posted, that’s next week, and it’s already been postponed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We’re now a couple of weeks into our third lockdown in the UK and we’re hoping we’ll get to take the trip in April now, fingers crossed.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Some 2021 Goals Guaranteed To Keep Me On Track</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/some-2021-goals-guaranteed-to-keep-me-on-track/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jpomfret.github.io/some-2021-goals-guaranteed-to-keep-me-on-track/</guid><description>&lt;p>Well 2020 was certainly an interesting year. I’m pretty sure none of us could have predicted how the world would look now and it won’t be regarded as the best year ever. However, there were definitely still some bright points I’d like to make note of before setting some targets for 2021.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="looking-back-on-2020">Looking back on 2020&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>One of my biggest achievements of the year was being awarded &lt;a class="link" href="https://mvp.microsoft.com/en-us/PublicProfile/5003655?fullName=Jess%20Pomfret" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>MVP for Cloud and Datacenter Management&lt;/a> in February. I’m really proud of this and my ability to positively contribute to our data and PowerShell communities. Along with that I managed to publish 25 blog posts and added two videos to my &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC0D3eA_natUs91YcuPE_tLg" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>YouTube channel&lt;/a>.  I also gave 10 presentations, only one in person, and also sat on two diversity and inclusion panels. I’ve also continued to contribute to dbatools, dbachecks and other open source software.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Outside of the tech world, it was a year of cancelled plans and lockdowns.  I will say this gave me and my wife plenty of time to explore our local footpaths. I recorded over 460 miles of walking last year. Something we usually wouldn’t have had time for.  I also cycled just over 700 miles after getting a new bike in June.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="looking-forward-to-2021">Looking forward to 2021&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Now, I’m not going to say 2021 is going to be back to normal, who knows if we’ll ever go back to that normal.  However, I’m hopeful that things will be better than 2020, and I hope sooner rather than later we can get back to travelling and actually meeting up with people in person!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I’m going to set some targets to aim for that won’t depend on what 2021 looks like.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Publish 26 blog posts – this would average to one every fortnight. I also aim to publish at a regular cadence.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Create 10 YouTube videos – my short ‘life hack’ videos that I’ve published have got positive reviews. I aim to get more of those recorded and available on YouTube&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speaking – I don’t have a specific number target here, but I’d like to think I can beat last year&amp;rsquo;s total of 10 presentations. Perhaps even some at in person events?!?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Open source contributions – Again, no specific numbers here but just a goal to continue contributing. I also have some ideas for this area that need a little love and time, but I hope to work on those this year as well.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Cycle 1000 miles – this would be more than I’ve ever cycled in a year, but without a commute in 2020 I found a lot more time for cycling before/after work.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Duolingo streak – another non tech goal. I’ve been using Duolingo to work on my French and hope to keep the streak alive throughout 2021.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>All in all, I hope 2021 is an improvement on 2020 – here’s to doing everything I can to make it a good one. I&amp;rsquo;ll leave you with a couple of local views I&amp;rsquo;ve enjoyed while cycling\walking this past year.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/p/CDhAVEXBjLq/?utm" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://www.instagram.com/p/CDhAVEXBjLq/?utm&lt;/a>_source=ig_web_copy_link&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/p/CAP8ta7huch/?utm" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://www.instagram.com/p/CAP8ta7huch/?utm&lt;/a>_source=ig_web_copy_link&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>T-SQL Tuesday #126 – Folding@Home</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#126-foldinghome/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#126-foldinghome/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://glennsqlperformance.com/2020/05/05/t-sql-tuesday-126-foldinghome/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/tsqltues.png"
loading="lazy"
alt="T-Sql Tuesday logo"
>&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Well it’s May T-SQL Tuesday time! Honestly I’m not sure if time is crawling or flying by, it seems like forever ago we got writing for the April prompt on unit testing databases.  Thanks to Glenn (&lt;a class="link" href="https://glennsqlperformance.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>b&lt;/a>|&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/GlennAlanBerry" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>t&lt;/a>) this month for hosting an interesting topic. I’m looking forward to reading all the responses. Also a bigger thanks for publicising &lt;a class="link" href="https://foldingathome.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Folding@Home&lt;/a> and setting up the &lt;a class="link" href="https://stats.foldingathome.org/team/236388" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>#SQLFamily&lt;/a> team!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Glenn wants to know what we’re doing in response to COVID-19 and if we’re contributing to the FAH #SQLFamily team, what our experience has been.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="foldinghome">&lt;strong>Folding@Home&lt;/strong>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I installed the Folding@Home client almost a month ago now on my Intel NUC. The NUC is connected up to my TV and mainly used as a media server. Occasionally I’ll use it to build out a lab to test something but most of the time it’s idle. Perfect to donate.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My FAH setup is pretty standard. I installed the client, requested a passkey, and set it loose. One thing I am a little uncomfortable with is the CPU is at 100% all the time FAH is running a workload, and it gets a little hot.  I started manually setting the workload to ‘finish’ (finish the workload currently running but then pause) in the evenings and then setting it back to ‘fold’ in the morning.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since I’m human, sometimes I forgot.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Enter PowerShell.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I found that you could pass commands into the FAHClient.exe and therefore set the status from PowerShell.  I created a simple module &lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/jpomfret/PSFah" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>PsFah&lt;/a> with a function to control the FAH client Status. When I say simple, it currently has one function that sets the local client status to fold, pause or finish. Perhaps I’ll add more over time (I started getting more side-tracked by this and then realised I needed to actually write this post).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I then set up two scheduled tasks (details below) that set the client to start folding at 7am and then set it to finish folding at 8pm. Removing the human, and therefore improving the process.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$taskSplat = @{
Action = New-ScheduledTaskAction -Execute PowerShell.exe -Argument &amp;lsquo;Set-FahStatus -Status Fold&amp;rsquo;
Trigger = New-ScheduledTaskTrigger -Daily -At &amp;lsquo;07:00&amp;rsquo;
Description = &amp;lsquo;Start Folding&amp;rsquo;
Principal = New-ScheduledTaskPrincipal -UserID &amp;ldquo;NT AUTHORITY\SYSTEM&amp;rdquo; -LogonType ServiceAccount -RunLevel Highest&lt;/p>
&lt;p>}
Register-ScheduledTask @taskSplat -TaskName &amp;lsquo;Start Folding&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$taskSplat = @{
Action = New-ScheduledTaskAction -Execute PowerShell.exe -Argument &amp;lsquo;Set-FahStatus -Status Finish&amp;rsquo;
Trigger = New-ScheduledTaskTrigger -Daily -At &amp;lsquo;20:00&amp;rsquo;
Description = &amp;lsquo;Finish Folding&amp;rsquo;
Principal = New-ScheduledTaskPrincipal -UserID &amp;ldquo;NT AUTHORITY\SYSTEM&amp;rdquo; -LogonType ServiceAccount -RunLevel Highest
}
Register-ScheduledTask @taskSplat -TaskName &amp;lsquo;Finish Folding&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="community-involvement">&lt;strong>Community Involvement&lt;/strong>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://i0.wp.com/jesspomfret.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/DW_Speaker-1.jpg?fit=650%2C640&amp;amp;ssl=1"
loading="lazy"
alt="data weekender camper van"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another way I’ve been trying to give back a little is with community involvement. I was lucky enough to be selected to speak as part of the &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.dataweekender.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Data Weekender&lt;/a> event. It was great to be able to deliver a session and share some dbatools knowledge. It was even better to watch some sessions and chat with the community. I miss that interaction that you get at conferences, and this day helped to fill that void – if only virtually.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am also really excited to be speaking at the &lt;a class="link" href="https://groupby.org/may2020-schedule/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>GroupBy conference&lt;/a>, which when this post goes live will be today!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I enjoy travelling and speaking and I was really disappointed that I had been selected to speak at a couple of events that were then cancelled because of COVID. Being able to still speak and contribute to the community virtually has been a really great experience.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="finally">Finally&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It’s easy to feel like you’re not doing enough during this crisis. it’s hard to stay motivated and to be productive when there is so much stress and anxiety in the world.  First things first, we have to look after ourselves and our people. If you have extra energy left over there are plenty of ways to give back, but it’s important for all of us to remember that just surviving right now takes more energy than usual.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Stay safe folks.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>T-SQL Tuesday #122 – Imposter Syndrome</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#122-imposter-syndrome/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#122-imposter-syndrome/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://jonshaulis.com/index.php/2020/01/07/t-sql-tuesday-122-imposter-syndrome/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/tsqltues.png"
loading="lazy"
>&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What a great topic for the start of the year as we’re all thinking about goal setting and personal improvement. Thanks to Jon Shaulis (&lt;a class="link" href="https://jonshaulis.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>b&lt;/a>|&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/JonShaulis" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>t&lt;/a>) for hosting this first monthly blog party of the decade.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Imposter syndrome is mentioned so often in our community, and it’s really interesting to me the wide number of people, who I consider experts, that say they still feel this sometimes. I’m really excited to read about how other people combat this feeling and hopefully pick up some tips for when it creeps into my head.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I’ve only been speaking and blogging for a couple of years now and I’ve found myself most often feeling like an imposter as I’m getting ready for a presentation. The scenario I imagine the most is that an attendee asks a question that I don’t have an answer for, or even worse points out a mistake I made or something I said that isn’t true.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To combat these feelings I try and prepare as fully as I can for my presentation, including reading and re-reading any Microsoft Docs on the topic. Also if others in the community have written blogs on the topic I try and read those too. To be honest though, I learn best by doing so as I’m getting ready for a presentation I make sure I work through my demos and fully understand what is happening in a lab environment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On the other side, I have to accept that there could be questions that I can’t answer, and instead of stuttering and panicking I just say something along the lines of, ‘Great question. I’ve got no idea, but I’ll find out and let you know’. First, this is a great way to generate content for blog posts. Second – you’ll gain the respect from the audience that you didn’t just try and make something up on the spot.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hopefully as I speak more and gain confidence in my ability these feelings will subside. However, it’s also possible it’ll always be in the back of my mind. Perhaps it’s a good thing- if I didn’t experience this maybe I wouldn’t be as well prepared for presentations and I’d do the audience a disservice by being overconfident in my ability.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>T-SQL Tuesday #121 - Gifts received for this year</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#121-gifts-received-for-this-year/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#121-gifts-received-for-this-year/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://curiousaboutdata.com/2019/12/03/tsql-tuesday-121-gifts-received-for-this-year/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/tsqltues.png"
loading="lazy"
>&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This is a time for material gift giving, for many of us. It might also be a time to consider the many gifts we have received through the year, and perhaps use this opportunity to appreciate people or situations that we were blessed with.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When I first saw Mala’s post last week for the last T-SQL Tuesday of the year I immediately started thinking of all the gifts I have received this year and how thankful I was with how 2019 has turned out. So first things first, thanks to Mala (&lt;a class="link" href="https://curiousaboutdata.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>b&lt;/a>|&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/sqlmal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>t&lt;/a>) for hosting this final prompt of 2019.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-gift-of-sqlfamily">The gift of #SQLFamily&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Around this time I found my local user group in Cleveland and started attending meetings. Attending meetings, talking to no one and going home, but still learning a lot from the great speakers and topics that were shared. This really started my journey as I started to interact with the community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was also starting to follow members of the SQL Server community on Twitter. I occasionally used the &lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/sqlhelp?src=hashtag_click" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>#SQLHelp&lt;/a> hashtag to get some guidance, but mostly played the role of lurker. I’d read articles that were shared, learning plenty, but not fully realizing the potential here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 2015 I changed jobs, which meant in 2016 I had the chance to attend my first PASS Summit. What an experience. It was like our local user group on steroids, all day, for 3 whole days.  I was exhausted by the end of the week and that was just from the conference portion as I mostly kept to myself during the evenings.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As time went on I still attended my local user group almost every month. I started talking to the people there more and more and began to understand this concept of #SQLFamily that I had heard mentioned so many times before.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My friends at the user group continually provided support, guidance, and encouragement and eventually I started to believe I could give something back to the community. I started this blog in February 2018 and gave my first user group presentation in June 2018. This is when I really started to believe in the magic of the #SQLFamily.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since that slightly shaky presentation on Data Compression in June 2018, I’ve presented 3 different sessions a total of 14 times at various user groups, SQL Saturdays and conferences. Although I still feel like I have a long way to go, it was really great to present back to my local user group this last month to show them I’m getting better and their support is working!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I will also give a special shout out to the Grillen guys. In June 2019 I was lucky enough to present my DSC &amp;amp; SQL Server presentation at DataGrillen. This was my first big conference- I had a few SQL Saturdays under my belt but this felt huge. William (&lt;a class="link" href="http://williamdurkin.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>b&lt;/a>|&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/sql_williamd" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>t&lt;/a>) and Ben (&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.solisyon.de/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>b&lt;/a>|&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/bweissman" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>t&lt;/a>) were the most amazing hosts, not only having created an amazing space to present and learn in, but also ensuring both myself and my wife had the best trip possible. I highly recommend checking this conference out if you can. The good news is, at this time, the c&lt;a class="link" href="https://datagrillen.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>all for speakers for 2020&lt;/a> is still open for 5 more days!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We are so lucky to live and work in a community that has this concept of #SQLFamily. It took me a while to see it but now I can truly appreciate it and I can honestly say I wouldn’t be where I am today without every one of you!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-gift-of-supportive-family--friends">The gift of supportive family &amp;amp; friends&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The second gift I will talk about is I have the most supportive friends and family. Thanks to the #SQLFamily, I have met and made connections with folks from all over the world.  Thanks to Twitter, I randomly stumbled across this tweet one afternoon:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/SQLDiplomat/status/1161342206675955713" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://twitter.com/SQLDiplomat/status/1161342206675955713&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I’m originally from Chippenham in the South West of England (about 1.5 hours from Southampton), and my wife, who’s American, wasn’t opposed to living in England at some point in our lives. Although it wasn’t in the immediate plan we decided to find out more and it turned out this opportunity was too good to miss. I’m really looking forward to 2020 and this new opportunity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I’m so excited to move back to England, to be closer to my family, and explore the UK and Europe with my wife. With the excitement comes absolute chaos as we prepare to move the 3,500 miles across the Atlantic. We’re currently working through selling our home, cars, things and packing up our lives in the US. We are very lucky to have the most supportive family on both sides of the pond as well as so many amazing friends that, although are sad to see us move, are being amazing at helping us realize (I guess it’s realise now!) this dream.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://i1.wp.com/jesspomfret.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/IMG-20191207-WA0002.jpg?fit=650%2C867&amp;amp;ssl=1"
loading="lazy"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Literally carrying me into 2020!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The final shoutout is to my wife, who to be fair has the rougher deal here. I am moving towards my family, with a job lined up that I’m excited about. She is stepping into a world of unknown, leaving her family and her dream job in the US for an adventure in England. You wouldn’t know this though, she’s the one keeping us organized and on track while I write blog posts to avoid packing ?. Her support and sense of adventure is the gift I’m most thankful for, as I know I couldn’t have accomplished half the things I did this year without her in my corner.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I’ve had a great 2019. It is ending in no way how I expected, and that’s largely due to the amazing gifts I’ve received from #SQLFamily and my own friends and family. So a big thank you to everyone involved!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I hope everyone has a safe and enjoyable holiday season. Thanks again Mala for hosting!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>National Coming Out Day</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/national-coming-out-day/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jpomfret.github.io/national-coming-out-day/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today, October 11th is National Coming Out Day in the United States. This (2019) will be the 31st anniversary of its founding by Robert Eichberg and Jean O&amp;rsquo;Leary. The idea was to raise awareness and support for the LGBT community. &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.hrc.org/resources/national-coming-out-day" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>If you know someone who identifies as LGBT you are more likely to support equal rights&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Most people think they don&amp;rsquo;t know anyone gay or lesbian, and in fact, everybody does. It is imperative that we come out and let people know who we are and disabuse them of their fears and stereotypes.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>– Robert Eichberg, in 1993&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.nytimes.com/1995/08/15/obituaries/robert-eichberg-50-gay-rights-leader.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>[3]&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>When I first heard about National Coming Out Day I was in college and I didn’t really get it. Why did we need a day to celebrate coming out? Can’t people just do it when they’re ready, or not? Shout out to the &lt;a class="link" href="http://workingwithdevs.com/tsql2sday-119-changing-your-mind/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>#tsql2sday&lt;/a> prompt from this month, which was about changing your opinion on something - I’ve changed my mind on this too.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="why-is-national-coming-out-day-important">&lt;strong>Why is National Coming Out Day Important?&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Firstly, for yourself – trying to hide a part of who you are is exhausting. Trying to constantly cover your tracks or not talking about the great weekend you had with your partner or LGBT friends makes you feel guarded and unwilling to fully integrate into conversations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A friend once told me about a diversity and inclusion exercise where they go around the group and have to talk about their weekend without revealing their partners gender, which is harder than you might think – and that was just one conversation. Now try doing it all day! &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Secondly, for everyone behind you. This is the magic if you ask me. The more people that are out the more it becomes normal. As we already mentioned, if you know someone who is LGBT, or really of any diverse group, you are much more likely to try to understand and to be cognizant of things that affect them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It also creates role models for the next generation. Usually when we mention role models we think of actors/actresses, sports stars and celebrities. When there are LGBT people in the limelight it’s exciting, it’s cool to know &amp;ldquo;hey that person is like me, maybe this will be alright&amp;rdquo;. I’d like to argue the more important role models are the regular people like you and me. Just going about our daily lives, trying to adult.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This isn’t about my personal coming out story. I am not looking for praise on coming out or being out. This is just about my regular, everyday life. I don’t hide who I am, what you get all the time is me, a slightly socially awkward lesbian IT nerd with a great sense of humour (depending on who you ask, but I like to think so). &lt;/p>
&lt;p>I got married almost a year ago now. We both have jobs we enjoy, we bought a house, we have two cats. It’s all pretty ordinary. – my hope is that by making it normal it’ll be easier for the next group of people coming behind us. Anyone who feels like they don’t fit in for whatever reason, or has feelings they don’t understand. can look around and see people like them, making it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of the posts that came out of #tsql2sday prompt mentioned this exact idea, “Representation matters”. First go queue this link up to read next, it’s excellent. “&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.sqlgene.com/2019/10/08/what-convinced-me-that-diversity-is-important/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>What Convinced me that diversity is important&lt;/a>”. In the post Eugene talks about his own type of diversity, and how his life was impacted by seeing successful people like him. This simple act of living your life openly really can make a difference for people.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now this is not an encouragement for everyone currently in the closet to just come out and join the party. It’s a big step and it’s not all unicorns and rainbows out here. It’s vital that you are safe and have the support you need. At the end of the day, you do you, because every situation is different.  If you need someone in your corner feel free to reach out to me. I’m definitely no expert but I’ll do my best.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, if you feel so inclined head over to &lt;a class="link" href="http://amtwo.lgbt" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>http://amtwo.lgbt&lt;/a> and take a look at my good friend Andy’s post. He’s currently raising money for &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.thetrevorproject.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>The Trevor Project&lt;/a>, an organization whose mission is to end suicide among gay, lesbian, bisexual, transgender, queer &amp;amp; questioning young people. Also, he has the “Unofficial Queer Guide to PASS Summit”, if you’re heading there next month.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks for reading – and happy National Coming Out Day!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>2018 Comes to a Close</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/2018-comes-to-a-close/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jpomfret.github.io/2018-comes-to-a-close/</guid><description>&lt;p>2018 has been an amazing year for me. I never imagined when I started this blog in February that I would be going into 2019 even more excited to give back to the community. Public speaking is not something that comes easy to me, and in fact I find it pretty terrifying, which is why I’m amazed at how much I enjoyed presenting this past year.  The SQL Server community is definitely a special group of professionals, so thank you to any and all of you who have made this year one of my best yet.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now I’m all about goals and targets so in May I wrote a T-SQL Tuesday post about giving back to the community and I set several goals to complete in 2018, let’s review.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="10-blog-posts-on-jesspomfretcom-3-technical">10 blog posts on jesspomfret.com (3 technical)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This year end summary makes 12 posts for the year, and 7 were technical posts. My most popular post was ‘&lt;a class="link" href="https://jesspomfret.com/checking-backups-with-dbachecks/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Checking backups with dbachecks&lt;/a>’.  I also contributed a guest post on the dbatools blog covering &lt;a class="link" href="https://jesspomfret.com/checking-backups-with-dbachecks/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>migrating application databases.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="50-prs-to-dbatoolsdbachecks">50 PR’s to dbatools/dbachecks&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This goal was to encourage contributions to open source projects.  My involvement with dbatools and dbachecks is what got me started down this path of blogging and speaking so I wanted to make sure I didn’t lose sight of that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So far in 2018 I have 40 pull requests to dbatools and 12 to dbachecks, so I have met my goal here with a few days to spare.  I also contributed to a few other open source projects this year, I had 3 PRs accepted to the Microsoft Sql-Docs repository, and I have 2 open PRs to the SqlServerDsc module.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="1-user-group--1-other-presentation">1 user group &amp;amp; 1 ‘other’ presentation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This goal I surprised myself with, I thought this would be the hardest one to meet and it ended up being the most rewarding.  I presented my &lt;a class="link" href="https://jesspomfret.com/first-user-group-presentation-i-survived/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>first ever session&lt;/a> to the Ohio North SQL Server User Group in June, it went ok. My topic was data compression and I found myself sweating, rushing and a little short on content.  With some amazing feedback and support I added some content and delivered it again at SQL Saturday Columbus and it went much better. I then presented it for a third time to the DBA Fundamentals Virtual chapter, which was good although a little strange not being able to see your audience.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also presented a PSPowerHour lightening talk on apply data compression with dbatools, I’d say I well exceeded this goal.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="looking-forward-to-2019">Looking forward to 2019&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My main goal for 2019 is to improve my blog, regular content is going to be the most important part of increasing my traffic so I’m going to aim for 26 blog posts in 2019.  I’m also excited to already have two speaking engagements on the calendar as I aim for 5 presentations this year. My data compression session has been accepted to SQL Saturday Cleveland, and a new session I’m working on ‘Installing SQL Server with PowerShell DSC’ was selected for DataGrillen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I hope everyone has a great last few days of 2018 and starts 2019 strong.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cheers!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>T-SQL Tuesday #99 - Door #1</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#99-door-%231/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#99-door-%231/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://sqlblog.org/2018/02/06/t-sql-tuesday-99" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/mjtuesday.png"
loading="lazy"
alt="MJTuesday"
>&lt;/a>First off, welcome to my first T-SQL Tuesday which seems like the perfect first blog post to introduce myself and my non-SQL Server life.  Starting this blog and becoming more involved with the SQL Server community (read speaking) is my goal for 2018 so here goes nothing. Thanks to &lt;a class="link" href="http://twitter.com/AaronBertrand" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Aaron Bertrand&lt;/a> for hosting and picking a great topic.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was born in Oxford, England before my family moved to the small market town of &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/chippenham" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Chippenham, Wiltshire&lt;/a> where I was raised.  Leading to my main passion being proper football. We can argue about why this is the proper football in a later post perhaps (hint: you use your feet to kick a ball, no hands or egg-shaped objects here).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My earliest memories involve playing and watching football. When I was in primary school (equivalent of elementary school in the USA) my mum fought with the headmistress until I was allowed to play on the boy’s team.  The boys weren’t particularly happy until they realized I could hold my own.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I then played for Chippenham Town Ladies for many seasons while I was in Secondary School and earned appearances for the Wiltshire County team.  Next I joined the Bristol Academy of Sport at Filton College for the 2003/2004 season and played for Bristol Rovers Ladies.  This set up my big move across the pond as I was recruited to join &lt;a class="link" href="http://gozips.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>The University of Akron Zips&lt;/a> in 2005.  After four fantastic years of playing football every day and traveling around the United States, I graduated in 2009 with a degree in Information Systems and eBusiness, followed by an MBA.  Then in 2011 accidentally became a DBA for a direct marketing company in Akron.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I have since moved employers but still reside in Northeast Ohio as a SQL Server DBA.  My days of playing football are behind me, but I now spend more time than I probably should watching the English Premier League and worrying about my &lt;a class="link" href="https://fantasy.premierleague.com/a/team/991342" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>fantasy (proper) football&lt;/a> team. I also enjoy watching US sports, hiking, Crossfiting and travelling with my partner, Kelcie.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[gallery type=&amp;ldquo;rectangular&amp;rdquo; link=&amp;ldquo;none&amp;rdquo; size=&amp;ldquo;medium&amp;rdquo; columns=&amp;ldquo;2&amp;rdquo; ids=&amp;ldquo;52,53,54&amp;rdquo;]&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>