<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>football on Jess Pomfret</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/tags/football/</link><description>Recent content in football on Jess Pomfret</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jpomfret.github.io/tags/football/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>T-SQL Tuesday #99 - Door #1</title><link>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#99-door-%231/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jpomfret.github.io/t-sql-tuesday-#99-door-%231/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://sqlblog.org/2018/02/06/t-sql-tuesday-99" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;img src="https://jpomfret.github.io/images/mjtuesday.png"
loading="lazy"
alt="MJTuesday"
>&lt;/a>First off, welcome to my first T-SQL Tuesday which seems like the perfect first blog post to introduce myself and my non-SQL Server life.  Starting this blog and becoming more involved with the SQL Server community (read speaking) is my goal for 2018 so here goes nothing. Thanks to &lt;a class="link" href="http://twitter.com/AaronBertrand" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Aaron Bertrand&lt;/a> for hosting and picking a great topic.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was born in Oxford, England before my family moved to the small market town of &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/chippenham" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Chippenham, Wiltshire&lt;/a> where I was raised.  Leading to my main passion being proper football. We can argue about why this is the proper football in a later post perhaps (hint: you use your feet to kick a ball, no hands or egg-shaped objects here).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My earliest memories involve playing and watching football. When I was in primary school (equivalent of elementary school in the USA) my mum fought with the headmistress until I was allowed to play on the boy’s team.  The boys weren’t particularly happy until they realized I could hold my own.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I then played for Chippenham Town Ladies for many seasons while I was in Secondary School and earned appearances for the Wiltshire County team.  Next I joined the Bristol Academy of Sport at Filton College for the 2003/2004 season and played for Bristol Rovers Ladies.  This set up my big move across the pond as I was recruited to join &lt;a class="link" href="http://gozips.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>The University of Akron Zips&lt;/a> in 2005.  After four fantastic years of playing football every day and traveling around the United States, I graduated in 2009 with a degree in Information Systems and eBusiness, followed by an MBA.  Then in 2011 accidentally became a DBA for a direct marketing company in Akron.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I have since moved employers but still reside in Northeast Ohio as a SQL Server DBA.  My days of playing football are behind me, but I now spend more time than I probably should watching the English Premier League and worrying about my &lt;a class="link" href="https://fantasy.premierleague.com/a/team/991342" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>fantasy (proper) football&lt;/a> team. I also enjoy watching US sports, hiking, Crossfiting and travelling with my partner, Kelcie.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[gallery type=&amp;ldquo;rectangular&amp;rdquo; link=&amp;ldquo;none&amp;rdquo; size=&amp;ldquo;medium&amp;rdquo; columns=&amp;ldquo;2&amp;rdquo; ids=&amp;ldquo;52,53,54&amp;rdquo;]&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>